[The Age of Awakening]
[觉醒年代]
[Episode Forty-one]
[第四十一集]
Come, Runzhi.
来 润之
Sit.
坐
Give me a minute.
等我一下啊
Runzhi.
润之啊
How's the Zhang-expelling movement going in Hunan?
这个湖南的驱张运动搞得怎么样了
[Li Dazhao, styled Shouchang, Director of Peking University Library]
[李大钊 字 守常 北京大学图书馆主任]
Tell me about it quickly.
赶紧跟我说说啊
This Jin Yunpeng
这靳云鹏啊
has promised
已经答应了
to solve things in Hunan.
要解决湖南的事情
Now the warlords are fighting.
现在军阀混战
Zhang Jingyao is under attack from all sides.
张敬尧四面楚歌
[Mao Zedong, styled Runzhi]
[毛泽东 字 润之]
His defeat is inevitable.
败局已定
So Runzhi,
那么润之啊
after the Zhang-expelling movement,
驱张运动之后
where will Hunan go from here?
湖南将何去何从
Have you ever thought about it?
你想过吗
Sir.
先生
That's exactly what I want to ask you.
这也正是我要请教你的问题
No.
不
Actually, I want to hear your opinion.
我其实是想听听你的意见
There are two main questions I have in mind
这次驱张运动
for the Zhang-expelling movement.
我主要想的问题有两个
First,
第一
only by relying on the great unity of the people
只有依靠民众大联合
can the ideal of saving the country and the people be realized.
才能实现救国救民的理想
Second,
第二
the efforts to achieve Hunan autonomy
驱张运动后
after Zhang-expelling movement.
努力争取实现湖南自治
Very good, Runzhi.
好啊 润之
Here, hold this.
来 悟悟手
You've caught both of these practical problems.
这两个实际的问题都被你抓着了
Good!
好啊
About the way of action of the great unity of the people,
关于民众大联合的行动方式啊
there are two factions.
有两个主张
The first is the fierce faction of Marxism-Leninism.
第一 是马克思列宁的激烈派
The second is the moderates of Kropotkin.
第二 是克鲁泡特金的温和派
What about you, Runzhi?
那么你毛润之
Which faction are you with?
现在是哪个派啊
To tell the truth,
说实话
I'm struggling now.
我现在很纠结
I've read a lot
俄国十月革命的资料
about Russia's October Revolution.
我看了不少
I've put my heart on it.
心向往之
But emotionally speaking,
但是从情感上讲
I am still apprehensive
我对暴力革命
about violent revolution.
还是心有顾忌
I probably lean more towards
我可能更偏向于
moderate anarchist reformism.
无政府主义的温和改良
Then, Runzhi,
那么润之
how are you
你打算
going to improve Hunan?
怎么改良湖南呢
Right now, it's a warlord state.
现在是军阀混战
After Zhang is expelled,
驱张之后
there will be a new warlord governor.
还会迎来新的督军
I know
我知道
that you and Mr. Zhongfu
您和仲甫先生
both advocate the implementation of provincial autonomy.
都主张落实联省自治
So I was thinking,
所以我在想
can we take the lead in Hunan?
我们湖南能不能带个头
After expelling Zhang,
驱张成功之后
we first get rid of the control of the Northern Warlords
首先摆脱北洋军阀的控制
and establish a true government based on the people.
建立以民为主的真政府
Of course, this is just my idea.
当然 这也只是我的想法
I haven't figured it out yet.
还没有理出头绪
So I want to hear your opinion.
所以 想听听您的意见
Runzhi.
润之啊
Two questions.
两个问题
The first question,
第一个问题
I still suggest you
我还是建议你
learn more about the Russian October Revolution
再多去了解一些俄国的十月革命
and Marxist ideas.
还有马克思主义的思想
I might as well tell you explicitly.
我不妨明确地告诉你
I and Mr. Zhongfu
我和仲甫先生
now have a firm belief in Marxism.
都已经确定了马克思主义的信仰
We are determined to emulate Russia
我们决心效仿俄国
and take the socialist road,
走社会主义的道路
because history has proved that
因为历史已经证明
if China takes the road of reformism,
中国走改良的道路
nothing will work at all.
根本就行不通
Only the fundamental transformation of society
只有实现对于社会的根本改造
can save our country.
才可以挽救我们的国家
Scond question.
第二个问题
Runzhi, I suggest
润之我建议
putting your eyes further ahead.
把你的眼界放得更远一些
Consider the issue of transforming Hunan
把改造湖南这个问题
in the context of the overall plan
放到改造整个中国社会的
to transform the whole Chinese society.
大方案当中去思考
This will save you a lot of detours.
这样你会少走很多的弯路的
Actually, sir,
先生 其实
I admire Marxism and socialism very much.
我非常崇拜马克思主义和社会主义
Furthermore,
另外
I am also very interested in the Russian revolution.
我对俄国革命也是非常感兴趣的
I have already consulted with the comrades of Xinmin Society
我已经和新民学会的同志商量了
to prepare to set up a Russian research society in Changsha.
准备在长沙成立俄罗斯研究会
At the same time,
同时啊
I also go to Russia to study or work-study
我也去俄国留学或者勤工俭学
and study deeply
深刻地研究一下
to see if China is suitable to take the Russian road,
中国到底适不适合走俄国人的道路
and find this answer quickly.
并且 迅速地找到答案
Good!
好啊
Runzhi.
润之
I set up the Marxist Theory Research Institute in Peking University,
我在北大成立了马克思学说研究会
and with the support of Mr. Cai,
而且在蔡先生的支持之下
I also set up a communist bookstore.
我也搞了一个共产主义的书屋
In our bookstore,
我们那个书屋
there are many books on the Russian revolution
有很多俄国革命
and on Marxist theories,
还有马克思主义学说的书籍
and we often run recommended reading clubs.
而且经常开办推荐读书会
There will be a seminar tomorrow.
明天正好有一个讨论会
The topic of discussion is
讨论的主题就是
the "Communist Manifesto".
《共产党宣言》
Come and join us.
你来参加吧
Great.
太好了
I can't wait to see those books now.
我恨不得现在就看到那些书籍
Sir, I will definitely go.
先生 我一定去
Runzhi.
润之
Time waits for no man.
时不我待啊
We can't keep wandering at the crossroads.
我们不能总是在十字路口上徘徊了
It's time to make a decision.
到了该决断的时候了
[Kangmouyizhai, Beijing]
[北京 亢慕义斋]
Hello, Mr. Cai.
蔡先生好
Hello, classmates.
同学们好
[Cai Yuanpei, styled Jiemin, President of Peking University]
[蔡元培 字 孑民 北京大学校长]
I came to see everyone.
我过来看看大家
You all seem busy.
你们忙吧
Out of the laboratory and into prison.
出研究室入监狱
The South and North united stand strong.
南方兼有北方强
This pair of couplets hangs well.
这副对子挂得好啊
[Deng Zhongxia, styled Zhongxie, Student at Peking University]
[邓中夏 字 仲澥 北京大学学生]
The style has a very righteous cause to it.
很有些杀身成仁的风骨啊
Mr. Cai.
蔡先生
Mr. Shouchang.
守常先生
Why didn't you tell me when you came?
您来了怎么也不跟我说一声啊
Brother Shouchang, I heard
守常兄 我听说
the arrangement of the office of this Marxist Theory Research Society
这个马克思学说研究会的办公室啊
is very special.
布置得很特别
I just came to have a look.
我呢 就赶来参观一下
Isn't this Mao Runzhi from Hunan?
这不是湖南的毛润之吗
When did you come to Beijing?
什么时候来北京的
Why don't you come to see me?
怎么也不来看我
I often tell them about you.
我常向他们提起你哦
I have been in Beijing for some time.
我来北京有一段时间了
Come and have a seat.
来 请坐
Sit down.
您坐
Shouchang, please.
守常 请
I've been busy
我一直忙着
asking for the dismissal and punishment of Zhang Jingyao.
要求撤职惩办张敬尧的事情
So I haven't made time to visit you at Peking University.
所以一直没有腾出时间到北大看您
I hope you can forgive me, sir.
希望先生能见谅
Mr. Cai, do you know?
蔡先生 您知道吗
Runzhi is in Beijing now.
现在润之在北京啊
His has become a big name.
那可是大大的有名啊
The Zhang-expelling movement has turned into a raging fire,
驱张运动搞得那是风风火火
and by himself he started
而且自己还创办了
the Beijing-Hunan Federation from All Walks of Life
旅京湖南各界联合会
and Beijing-Hunan People from All Walks of Life's Zhang-expelling Committee,
和旅京湘人各界驱张委员会
and became
而且自己还当上了
the President of the Common People's News Agency.
平民通讯社的社长
I've already seen Mao Runzhi.
我早就看出毛润之啊
He is a man of great talent.
是个大才之人
Now is the time for young people to show their talents.
现在正是年轻人大显身手的时候
How's the Zhang-expelling movement going?
怎么样 驱张运动进行得如何
Victory is in sight.
胜利在望
Runzhi.
润之啊
You can take part in our activities more often,
你可以多参加我们的活动啊
see more socialism
多看一些社会主义
and the Russian October Revolution.
和俄国十月革命的书
I sincerely hope that
我是真心希望
you will soon
你能够早
become a Marxist.
成为一个马克思主义者
I think
我想
I am changing in the direction you want me to go.
我正在朝着先生所希望的方向转变
Good, we have the opportunity to talk more
好 有机会我们多聊聊
When are you going back?
打算件么时候回去啊
I intend
我打算
to go to Shanghai next month.
下个月去趟上海
You're going to Shanghai?
你要去上海
Do you want to go and see Zhongfu?
那你是不是要去看一下仲甫
If you're going,
如果你要去
please give him my regards.
请一定代我向他表示问候
Yes, definitely.
好的 一定
Actually,
其实啊
I'm full of questions.
我有一肚子的问题
I want to ask Mr. Zhongfu.
想去请教仲甫先生
I haven't seen him for over a year.
我有一年多没见他了
I really want to have a good chat with him.
真想跟他好好地聊一聊
Good.
好 好
Brother Shouchang.
守常兄
Mr. Cai,
蔡先生
what do you think?
怎么样
Do you think this place is OK?
你觉得这个地方还可以吗
This place is particularly nice.
这个地方特别好
This is a residential building.
这儿是民宅
We have many communist books.
我们很多共产主义书籍
They all can be put here.
都可以放在这儿
Save that Zhang Fengzai,
省得那个张丰载呀
who will make things difficult for us, check us again.
再刁难我们检查我们
Brother Shouchang,
守常兄啊
don't take it lightly.
不过还是不要掉以轻心
It's better to be cautious.
还是谨慎一些为好
I suggest this bookstore
我建议这个书屋啊
should have a more hidden name.
是不是能找一个更加隐蔽的名号
I have the name in mind.
名字我都想好了
Kangmuyizhai.
亢慕义斋
Kangmuyi?
亢慕义
Transliteration, and add a "zhai".
译音 再加个斋
Interesting for a communist bookstore.
有意思 共产主义书屋
Very wise.
很有智慧
This name is also very bold.
也很响亮这名字
I have something to do. I won't stay long.
我还有事 我就不久留了
Take care, Mr. Cai.
蔡先生慢走
Thank you.
好
You are all busy.
你们忙
Come, everybody.
来 大家
Put all the work away.
把手里的活都放一放
Let's get ready to start class.
咱们准备开始上课了
Everybody come back.
来 大家都回来吧
Today, is our Peking University
今天 是我们北京大学
Marxist Theory Research Society's
马克思学说研究会
first reading activity.
举办的第一场读书活动
Let's welcome Mr. Li Dazhao
下面呢 我们就有请李大钊先生
give a lecture on the "Communist Manifesto" for everyone.
为大家宣讲《共产党宣言》
Welcome.
大家欢迎
Students, the "Communist Manifesto"
同学们《共产党宣言》
was drafted by Karl Marx
是卡尔·马克思
and Friedrich Engels
和弗里德里希·恩格斯
as a program for the Communist League,
为共产主义同盟起草的纲领
then completed by Marx.
由马克思执笔完成
So as for the basic principles of this manifesto,
那么这个宣言的基本原理
I think it can be summarized as follows.
我觉得可以做如下的概括
In any historical period,
任何一个历史时期
the dominant mode of production and exchange
主要的生产方式和交换方式
and the resulting social structure
和由此必然产生的社会结构
are the foundations
都是这个历史时期当中
upon which the political and spiritual history
政治的 精神的历史
of that historical period is built.
所赖以确立的基础
Only from this basis,
只有从这个基础出发
can history be explained.
才能够解释历史
Since the disintegration of primitive human society,
自从原始人类社会解体以来
the whole history of mankind
人类的全部历史
is the history of class struggle.
都是阶级斗争的历史
This history includes
这个历史包括了
a series of developmental stages.
一系列的发展阶段
Now it has reached a stage
现在到了这么一个阶段
where the proletariat
即无产阶级
cannot liberate itself from bourgeois domination
如果不能同时使整个社会
if it cannot at the same time free society as a whole
摆脱资产阶级的压迫 剥削
from the oppression of the bourgeoisie,
阶级划分 阶级斗争
the division of the exploiting classes,
那么它自己就不能从
and class struggle.
资产阶级的统治当中解放出来
Eliminate private ownership,
消灭私有制
overthrow bourgeois rule,
推翻资产阶级统治
and let the proletariat seize power,
由无产阶级夺取政权
and then step by step,
然后一步一步地
seize all the capital of the bourgeoisie.
夺取资产阶级的全部资本
Then concentrate the means of production in the hands of the state,
然后把生产工具集中在国家
that is, the proletariat
即组织成为了统治阶级的
has become the rulling class.
无产阶级手中
And then as soon as possible,
然后尽可能快地
increase the total amount of productive forces.
增加生产力的总量
This is the basic point of view of the "Communist Manifesto".
这是《共产党宣言》的基本观点
In this revolution,
在这个革命当中
what the proletarians will lose is only their chains,
无产者失去的只是锁链
and they will get the whole world.
他们得到的将是整个世界
This is the "Communist Manifesto"'s
这是《共产党宣言》
last solemn declaration.
最后的庄严宣告
Mr. Shouchang.
守常先生
The Russian friend is here.
俄国朋友到了
Mr. Voitinsky.
维经斯基先生
Please come.
来 请
Students.
同学们
Today, attending the Marxist Theory Research Society,
今天来参加马克思学说研究会的
in addition to your colleagues,
除了各位同人之外
are Russian friends from afar.
还有远道而来的俄国朋友
[Grigori Voitinsky, Head of the Far Eastern Bureau]
[维经斯基 俄共（布）远东局代表]
So, next,
那么接下来
please ask the Russian Communist Party's
就请俄国共产党
Head of the Far East Bureau,
远东局的全权代表
Mr. Voitinsky.
维经斯基先生
Let him tell you all a bit about Russia.
来为大家介绍一下俄国的情况
Welcome.
大家欢迎
Comrades,
同志们
I am a member of the Far East Bureau of the Central Committee of the Russian Communist Party.
我是俄共中央远东局的成员
[Yang Mingzhai, Member of the Russian Communist Party]
[杨明斋 俄共党员]
This time, I am sent to China
这次受共产国际
by the Comintern and the Central Committee of the Russian Communist Party
和俄共中央的委派
to understand the situation
来到中国了解情况
and discuss some practical problems.
讨论一些实际问题
I heard that all of you here
我听说在座的各位
are activists who participated in the May Fourth Movement.
都是参加过五四运动的积极分子
I am very happy and honored.
我非常高兴和荣幸
I hope that in the future
我希望今后
I can often attend such meetings.
能经常参加这样的会议
I also hope that in the future
也希望今后
I can communicate more with you.
能和大家多沟通 多交流
Let me give you a brief introduction.
下面 我简单给大家介绍一下
The process of the October Revolution in Russia
俄国十月革命发生的过程
and some current situations in Russia.
和俄国现在的一些情况
[2 Old Yuyangli, French Concession, Shanghai]
[上海法租界老渔阳里2号]
Not half bad.
挺好
Zhongfu.
仲甫
I think Mr. Xingyan's arrangement is right.
我觉得行严先生安排的是对的
The situation in Guangzhou is so tense now.
广州现在局势那么紧张
[Wang Mengzou, Manager of East Asia Library]
[汪孟邹 亚东图书馆经理]
It will be dangerous for you to go to Southwest University.
你去西南大学会有危险
[Zhao Shiyan, styled Qinsheng]
[赵世炎 字 琴生]
So what does he suggest?
所以他建议呢
Stay in Shanghai for a few more days.
你在上海多待些日子
That makes two of us.
我也是这么想的
It may not be a bad idea
也好
Is this the third home of "New Youth"?
这是《新青年》的第三个家了吧
My first home is my East Asia Library.
第一个家是我的亚东图书馆
Fu Huali in Jiangxi Road.
江西路的福华里
What about this second home?
这第二个家呢
You are at 9 Jiangan Hutong in Beijing.
就是你在北京的箭杆胡同9号
2 Old Yuyangli.
老渔阳里2号
This is Bai Wenwei's old house.
这是柏文蔚的旧宅
It used to be our Hunan-Anhui Comrade Association.
也曾经是我们湘皖同志会
A gathering place.
集结的地方
This is the third home.
这是第三个家
There will be a fourth and a fifth.
还会有第四个 第五个
This "New Youth" has gone around.
这《新青年》 走了一圈
Come back again.
又回来了
You Chen Duxiu
你陈独秀
have came back after a walk.
走了一圈也回来了
How wonderful this life is!
这个人生多么奇妙啊
"New Youth" and Chen Duxiu
《新青年》和陈独秀
although they are all back,
虽然都回来了
but not anymore
但是已经不是
the original "New Youth"
原来的《新青年》
and Chen Duxiu.
和陈独秀了
They will all be reborn here.
他们都将在此 获得新生
Zhongfu, I think you should take advantage of this opportunity
仲甫 我看你就利用这个机会
to take the child and Junman over.
把孩子和君曼都接过来
Didn't Chen Jiongming send a special letter
那个陈炯明不是给北洋政府
to the Beiyang government?
去了专函了吗
I miss Wu Bingxiang.
我想那吴炳湘
He won't embarrass Junman either.
他也不会为难君曼的
It's good for Junman and the children to come.
君曼和孩子们过来固然好
But the most urgent thing at the moment
但眼下最迫切的
is to get "New Youth"
是《新青年》
new help in Shanghai.
在上海需要新帮手
Sir, I and Xu Deheng are here this time
先生 我和许德珩这次来
to represent the Beijing Federation of Students in Shanghai's
就是代表北京学联来上海参加
preparatory work for the National Federation of All Walks of Life.
全国各界联合会的筹备工作
We can help you.
我们可以帮您
Good!
好啊
sir.
先生
"New Youth" has blossomed everywhere now.
《新青年》现在已经遍地开花
Deeply rooted in the hearts of the people.
深入人心了
I have a friend named Zhou Enlai.
我有个朋友叫周恩来
Not long ago he told me,
前不久他跟我说
because he read "New Youth",
他正是因为看了《新青年》
it has broadened his horizons and changed his destiny.
眼界大开 改变了命运
Zhou Enlai, I heard Shouchang talk about him.
周恩来 我听守常说过他
What is he doing now?
他现在在干什么
In Tianjin,
在天津
he was arrested for organizing demonstrations and petitions.
因为组织示威请愿活动被捕了
But they turned the cell into a laboratory,
不过他们把牢房变成了研究室
studying Marxism every day.
每天都在研究马克思主义
Before I came to Shanghai,
我来上海之前
I just asked someone to hand them
刚刚托人给他们梢去了
the lastest issue of "New Youth".
上一期的 《新青年》
Okay, right now
好 我们现在呀
we need young elites
就是需要这样的青年精英
to join our ranks.
加入到我们这个行列里来
Shiyan, when are you going to France?
世炎 你什么时候去法国
Around the beginning of May.
大概五月初
Well, it's still in a while.
那还好 还有一段时间
This time I just want to prepare
这段时间我正好想筹备
Marxist Theory Research Society.
马克思主义研究会
Come and join us.
你来参加吧
Okay, I'll definitely attend.
好我一定参加
Also,
还有
you can also help me edit "New Youth".
你也可以帮我编辑《新青年》
I heard Shouchang say,
我听守常说
haven't you been to Changxindian?
你不是去过长辛店吗
I want to write an issue recently,
我最近想编写一期
a special commemorative issue of May Day.
五一劳动节的纪念专号
You can show me around some factories.
你可以带我去一些工厂转转
Great, sir.
太好了先生
What do you think of the workers' movement now?
您现在怎么对工人运动
So interested?
这么感兴趣了
Not mildly interested.
不是一般地感兴趣
I am very interested.
是非常感兴趣
Shiyan.
世炎
Have you read the "Communist Manifesto"?
你读过《共产党宣言》吗
I do, I read it frequently.
读过 经常读 常读常新
It's just that no one has yet
只不过现在还没有人
translated it into Chinese.
能把它翻译成中文版本
If there is a Chinese version,
如果有了中文版本
we can give a speech in the factory.
咱们就可以到工厂里面演讲了
With no Chinese version,
没有中文版
you can still go to the factory to lecture.
也一样可以去工厂宣讲
A spectre. The spectre of communism
一个幽灵 共产主义的幽灵
wanders around Europe.
在欧洲游荡
To carry out a holy siege against this spectre,
为了对这个幽灵进行神圣的围巢
all forces of old Europe,
旧欧洲的一切势力
the Pope, the Tsar, Metternich, Guizot,
教皇和沙皇 梅特涅和基佐
French radicals, and German police
法国的激进派和德国的警察
are all united.
都联合起来了
Communists
共产党人
disdain to conceal one's own views and intentions.
不屑于隐满自己的观点和意图
They publicly announced
他们公开宣布
their beliefs
他们的自的
can only be achieved
只有用暴力
by violently overthrowing
推翻全部现存的社会制度
the entire existing social system.
才能达到
Let the ruling class
让统治阶级
tremble in front of the communist revolution.
在共产主义革命面前发抖吧
In this revolution, what the proletarians lose
无产者在这个革命中
are only their chains.
失去的只是锁链
They will get the whole world.
他们获得的将是整个世界
All hunger strikers will never give up.
全体绝食 不达自的 誓不罢休
[Tianjin Police Department Prison]
[天津警察厅监狱]
All hunger strikers--
全体绝食
Students, students.
同学们 同学们
Students, students, listen to me.
同学们 同学们听我说
You haven't eaten for two days.
你们已经两天没进食了
Shangfeng is in a hurry.
上峰很着急
Your classmates and parents are also very anxious.
你们的同学和父母也都很着急
Please be quiet.
请大家少安丹躁
Stop the hunger strike
先进食
and we will try our best to meet your requirements.
我们一定会尽量满足你们的要求的
Good.
好
There are three requirements for us.
我们的要求一共有三条
First, public trial as soon as possible,
第一条 尽快公审
give the students a statement according to the law of the Republic of China.
按民国约法给同学们一个说法
Second,
第二
improve detention conditions,
改善拘留条件
set up a special room
辟出专门的房间
and make sure the arrested students are separated from other prisoners
确保被捕同学与其他犯人分开
to live together in the same place and move freely.
集体同住一处 自由往来
Third, give the arrested students
第三 为被捕同学
the provided list of newspaper materials and books.
提供所开列的报刊资料和图书
Make sure students do exercises in groups,
确保同学们有集体做操
have collective study, discussions,
集体学习 讨论
and freedom of speech.
演讲 演戏的自由
We will never give up until we get what we want.
不达自的 我们决不罢休
Never give up until we get what we want!
不达自的 决不罢休
Students, students.
同学们 同学们
Students.
同学们
I have already reported your request to my boss.
你们的要求我已经向上头汇报了
Never stop!
誓不罢休
Never give up until we get what we want!
不达自的 决不罢休
Students, listen to me.
同学们听我说
Students, everyone listen to me. Listen to me!
同学们都听我说 听我说
Good news, good news.
好消息 好消息
The above authorities have all agreed to your requirements.
上头已经全部答应你们的要求了
Now everyone can eat.
现在 大家可以进食了
We won!
我们胜利了
Students.
同学们
Prison can also be our laboratory.
监狱也可以是我们的研究室
What about today's speech?
今天的演讲呢
Let me tell you about it.
由我来给大家讲一讲
Marx's historical materialism.
马克思的唯物史观
Marx's historical materialism has two main points.
马克思的唯物史观有两个要点
First is the description of the experience of human civilization.
其一是关于人类文明的经验的说明
Second is the theory of evolution of social organization.
其二是社会组织进化论
Marx believed
马克思认为
the sum of human social relations of production
人类社会生产关系的总和
constituted the structure of the social economy.
构成社会经济的构造
This is the basic structure of society,
这是社会的基础构造
that is, productivity.
也就是生产力
As soon as productivity changes,
生产力一有变化
society must change with it.
社会组织必须随着它变化
Social organizations as relations of production.
社会组织即生产关系
is the same as our food and clothing.
它也和布帛菽粟一样
It is the product of human output according to productivity.
是人类依生产力产出的产物
Feudal societies produce princes.
手臼产出封建诸侯的社会
Capitalist societies
蒸气制粉机
produce steam mill industries.
产出产业的资本家的社会
Productivity determines the relations of production.
生产力决定生产关系
When the relations of production cannot satisfy
当生产关系不能满足
the requirements of the development of productive forces,
生产力发展的要求的时候
it is necessary to break the old production relations
就需要去打破这种旧的生产关系
and the shackles of the old social organizations on the new productive forces.
旧社会组织对新生产力的束缚
and create
产出新的
new production relations that adapt to the development of productive forces.
适应生产力发展的生产关系
This is social revolution.
这就是社会革命
Human society
人类的社会
is the continuous development of productive forces,
就是通过生产力不断地发展
that constantly break the old relations of production
不断地去打破旧的生产关系
to create
产出新的
new production relations adapted to the development of productive forces,
适应生产力发展的生产关系
in order to realize the continuous development of society
来实现社会不断地
from the lower stage to the higher stage.
从低级阶段向高级阶段发展
This is Marx's unique historical materialism.
这就是马克思独特的唯物史观
29 January 1920.
一九二〇年一月二十九日
Until 17 July,
至七月十七日
in a Tianjin prison, young Zhou Enlai
青年周恩来在天津的监狱里
completed his ideological breakthrough.
完成了思想的裂变
The sprout of a revolutionary consciousness
一种革命意识的萌芽
began at this time.
从这个时候开始了
I heard that not many people
听说现在对俄国人
[Peking University]
[北京大学]
are interested in Russians nowadays.
感兴趣的不多了
Not many people have gone to listen
维经斯基的演讲
Voitinsky's speech.
已经没有多少人去听了
Now it's just us people
现在只有我们
from the Marxist Theory Research Association
马克思学说研究会的人
as a loyal listeners.
才是忠实听众
No one else is coming.
其他人都不来了
Voitinsky put forward himself several times
维经斯基几次提出
to talk to you alone.
要和您单独面谈
He also said he wanted to talk about some important things.
还说要谈一些重要的事情
I know what he wants to talk to me about.
我知道他要跟我谈什么
But it's too big.
但是这件事太大了
I have to be considerate.
我得考虑周全才行
Listen to his tone.
听他的口气啊
He's already impatient.
已经不耐烦了
This afternoon, then.
那就今天下午吧
Zhongxie.
仲澥
Help me arrange it.
帮我安排一下
Very well.
好
What's Runzhi doing?
润之在干什么
Runzhi went to Qufu.
润之去曲阜了
He said he would go to the Confucius Temple in Qufu first,
他说他要先去曲阜的孔庙看看
then go to Shanghai.
然后再去上海
Go to Confucius Temple.
去孔庙
Interesting.
有点意思
Shouchang.
守常
Shizhi.
适之
Hello, Mr. Shizhi.
适之先生好
Morning.
早上好
Hello, sir.
先生好
[Hu Shi, styled Shizhi, Professor at Peking University]
[胡适 字 适之 北京大学教授]
Have you heard from Zhongfu?
有仲甫信儿吗
Yes, we often keep in touch.
有啊 我们经常联系
He is in Shanghai now.
他现在在上海
Concentrating on editing "New Youth"?
专心编辑《新青年》呢
How come I haven't heard from him?
怎么就我没他的消息啊
Shizhi, where can we find you?
适之 我们上哪儿找你啊
Every day,
你现在天天
you're following Dewey's tail.
围着杜威的屁股后头转
The day your sister-in-law Jun left,
君曼嫂子走的那天
I haven't seen you either.
也没见着你的人影啊
I did have something that day.
那天我确实有事情
I asked Dongxiu to see her off.
我让冬秀去送她了
I heard that Chen Jionglang
我听说陈炯朗
wanted to invite Zhongfu to Guangdong
想要把仲甫请去广东
to become the chief of the education department.
当教育厅的厉长
When will he leave?
他什么时候动身啊
Who did you hear that from?
你听谁说的
Brother Wang Mengzou wrote to me.
汪孟邹兄长来信说的
The news should be correct.
消息应该没错
If that's the case,
如果真是这样的话
I wish he would go to Guangzhou
我倒真希望他去广州
because it's much safer than Shanghai.
因为那儿比上海安全得多
As long as he doesn't toss around, he'll be safe everywhere.
只要他不折腾哪儿都安全
But our brother
但咱们这兄长
not toss around?
他能不折腾吗
Shouchang.
守常
I know you've been close to the Russians recently.
我知道你最近和俄国人走得很近
It's also very dangerous.
这也很危险啊
Shizhi.
适之
You are so close to the Americans.
你跟美国人走得这么近
Aren't you afraid of danger?
你就不怕危险啊
You know what people say about you now?
你知道现在大伙怎么说你吗
Please don't talk about me.
行行行 别说我了
I know you don't like what I say either.
我知道我说的你也不爱听
Do what you want. Okay?
爱怎么折腾怎么折腾吧 好吧
You may just do as you like.
你想怎样就怎样吧
Bye bye.
拜拜
Morning.
早上好
Sir, be careful.
先生小心
[2 Old Yuyangli, French Concession, Shanghai]
[上海法租界老渔阳里2号]
Put it on the table.
放桌子上
Sir.
先生
[Chen Wangdao, Editor of "New Youth"]
[陈望道 《新青年》编辑]
What baby do you have in this box?
您这箱子里面放的什么宝贝啊
Let me show you.
我来给你看看
Let me show you the baby.
给你看看什么宝贝
This is the English version of the "Communist Manifesto".
这是英文版的《共产党宣言》哪
Sir, this is really a treasure.
先生 这可真是宝贝呀
I got it from Li Dazhao.
我从李大钊那儿
Borrowed it through a back door.
走后门借来的
Wangdao.
望道
I give you two tasks today.
我今天给你两个任务
Say it, sir.
先生您说
First,
第一
edit "New Youth" with me.
跟我一起编辑 《新青年》
I intend to officially
我打算正式地
propose to my fellow editors in Beijing.
向北京的同人编辑们提出
that you be
由你来担任
the lead writer of "New Youth".
《新青年》的主笔
How can this be done?
这哪行啊
How can I compare with them?
我怎么能和他们相比
Sir, you flatter me too much.
先生 您太抬举我了
Why can't you?
你怎么不行啊
Now is the world of young people.
现在是青年人的天下
Hu Shizhi is known as a young scholar.
胡适之号称青年导师
I see
我看
that his thoughts
他的思想
are now five years behind "New Youth".
现在落后《新青年》五年
Be bold. It's okay.
大胆干 没事
I'll listen to you.
好 我听您的
Second.
第二
Take the time to translate the "Communist Manifesto"
抓紧时间把《共产党宣言》
into Chinese
翻译成中文版
and publish as soon as possible.
尽快出版
Great. I promise to live up to your mission.
太好了 保证不辱使命
I have the Japanese version.
我手上有日文版的
Now it's available in English.
现在又有了英文版
Check it out.
对照着看
This meaning can't be wrong.
这意思肯定就不会错
Let's divide the work.
咱们俩分工
You are in charge of translation.
你来负责翻译
Li Hanjun and I are in charge of proofreading.
我和李汉俊负责校对
This will make it faster.
这样能快点
That way.
那这样
I will go back to my hometown in Yiwu to translate.
我就回义乌老家去翻译
It's quieter there.
那儿比较安静
My mother took care of me again.
又有我母亲照顾
The efficiency will definitely be much faster.
效率肯定会快很多
Good.
好
Then I'll wait for you here.
那我就在这儿等你
Mr. Shouchang.
守常先生
[Beijing]
[北京]
Voitinsky is here.
维经斯基他们来了
Mr. Voitinsky.
维经斯基先生
Hello, hello.
你好你好
Nice to meet you again, Comrade Li Dazhao.
很高兴再次见到你李大钊同志
I'm glad you called me Comrade.
您叫我同志 我很高兴
But I think my consciousness
但是我觉得我的觉悟
haven't reached that level yet.
还没有到达那个层次
Come, come, sit down.
来来来请坐
Comrade Li Dazhao, you are too modest.
李大钊同志您太谦虚了
I have read many of your articles carefully.
我仔细拜读了您写的许多文章
Your level of Marxism,
您的马克思主义水平
[Grigori Voitinsky, Head of the Far Eastern Bureau]
[维经斯基 俄共（布）远东局代表]
even compared to Russia, has a high standard.
即使在俄国也具有很高的水准
But I think Marxists
但是我认为马克思主义者
should be more than just thinking,
不应该仅仅停留在思想上
it also should be reflected in action.
而更应该体现在行动上
I see what you mean.
我明白您的意思
We set up the Marxist Theory Research Society.
我们成立了马克思学说研究会
We also organized a survey on the current situation of workers in Changxindian.
也组织了长辛店工人现状调查
These are actions.
这些都是行动
These are not enough.
这些还是不够的
We believe that the present situation of the Chinese revolution
我们认为中国革命的现状
is to establish a proletarian political party as soon as possible.
是尽快成立无产阶级的政党
We have studied your situation carefully.
我们仔细研究了您的情况
I think you should take the lead.
认为应该由您来挑这个头
Let me give you something.
我送给您一样东西吧
This letter is for you.
这封信送给您
What's this?
这是什么
I found the right person for you.
这个合适的人 我帮您找着了
Who?
哪一位
Comrade Chen Duxiu.
陈独秀同志
Chen Duxiu.
陈独秀
Yes, that's him.
没错就是他
He is in Shanghai now.
他现在人在上海
Take this letter of mine to him.
您拿着我这封信去找他
Dear Comrade Li Dazhao.
亲爱的李大钊同志
I can see that you are interested in the party building.
能看出来您对建党这件事情
I already have a plan.
早就胸有成竹了
The founding of the Party will be an epoch-making event in China.
建党在中国是开天辟地的大事
How can we be careless?
我们哪能不慎重啊
Comrade.
同志
[Fenshuitang, Chengxi, Yiwu, Zhejiang]
[浙江义乌城西分水塘]
Wang.
望儿
Have a rest.
休息一会儿吧
I haven't moved all morning.
一上午都没动屁股了
Mom, why are you coming in again?
姆妈 你怎么又进来了
I thought we agreed.
不是说好了
Don't you call someone who can't come in
不叫不进来的吗
Wang.
望儿啊
What are you writing mysteriously?
你这神神秘秘的 写什么呀
You don't write in this room where our family is honored.
这放着咱家敬亮的堂屋你不写
I have to write it in this woodshed.
非要在这柴房写啊
It's quieter here.
这儿比较安静
Okay, mom.
好了 姆妈
Don't ask again.
你就不要再问了
Okay, okay, okay.
好 好 好
I cooked some zongzi.
我呀 煮了点粽子
Peel it and dip it in brown sugar.
剥好了 蘸着红糖吃
Delicious!
可好吃了
Good!
好啊
I happen to be a little hungry.
我正好有点饿了呢
Delicious.
好吃
Wang.
望儿啊
There's nothing left to wash.
还有没有要洗的呀
None.
没了
Wang.
望儿啊
What did you eat?
你 你吃什么了
This?
这
My silly son.
我的傻儿子
This brown sugar is not enough for you to dip.
这红糖还不够你蘸的
It looks like it's dipped in ink.
非要蘸着墨汁吃啊
We'll see.
你等着
Don't move, don't move, don't move
别动别动别动
My silly son.
我这傻儿子
Come on.
快来
Stop writing and wash up.
别写了快洗洗
Mom, mom, mom.
姆妈 姆妈
Put it here.
放这儿
Wash quickly.
快洗洗
Wang.
望儿啊
What's the taste of this ink?
这墨汁是什么味道呀
Sweet?
甜吧
Sweet.
甜
It tastes good.
味道好着呢
The taste of truth.
真理的味道
The taste of truth?
真 真理的味道
No more, right?
没有了吧
None.
好了
All right, mom.
好了，姆妈
What about you? Go and get busy.
您呢  去忙吧
Eat while it's hot, don't you?
抓紧吃 趁热吃不吃
Okay!
好嘞
[2 Old Yuyangli, French Concession, Shanghai]
[上海法租界老渔阳里2号]
Hennian, put Yingying in the cage quickly.
鹤年 赶紧把英英放到笼子里
Go to wash your hands and eat.
去洗手吃饭了啊
When will sister Bai Lan come?
妈 白兰姐姐什么时候来
Soon.
快了
Sister, help me put it on.
姐姐 帮我放一下
Sister Bai Lan said she would go to France in May.
白兰姐姐说 五月要去法国
We should arrive in Shanghai in a few days.
应该这几天就到上海了
Zhongfu, I forgot to tell you.
仲甫 我忘了跟你说
When I came back from Beijing,
我从北京回来的时候
Liu Haiwei told me
刘海威跟我说
he's going to be with Bai Lan.
他要和白兰在一起了
He said they would go to France together this time.
说是这次他们俩会一起去法国
I know good things.
我知道 好事
Haiwei goes abroad or I ask Mr. Cai for help.
海威出国还是我找蔡先生帮的忙
If the two of them can really be together,
他们两个要真是能在一起
we are relieved of Bai Lan.
我们对白兰也就放心了
Sir, madam.
先生 师母
Shiyan.
世炎
Zimei, Henian.
子美 鹤年
Hello, brother Shiyan.
世炎哥哥好
I brought you two acquaintances.
我给您带来了两位熟人
Who's coming in?
谁呀 快进来
[Shi Cuntong] [Yu Xiusong]
[施存统] [俞秀松]
Hello, Mr. Zhongfu.
仲甫先生好
Hello, madam.
夫人好
Hello.
你们好
Yu Xiusong. Shi Cuntong.
俞秀松 施存统
Great.
太好了
Sir.
先生
It's very kind of you to come.
你们能来真是太好了
Junman hurriedly added a few more dishes.
君曼 赶紧多添几个菜
We'll have two more drinks today.
今天我们要多喝两杯
Okay, okay, no problem.
好好好 没问题
Have a seat in your living room.
你们客厅坐吧
Come, come, please
来来来请
We came from Beijing this time.
先生 我们这次从北京赶过来
I went to you specially.
特意投奔您的
Now helping the "Weekly Review"--
现在在《星期评论》里边帮忙
You eat steamed stuffed bun firsts.
你两先吃包子啊
Sit, sit, sit, sit.
快坐 坐坐坐
Great. We need someone right now.
太好了 我们现在正需要人手
We are preparing to set up
我们正在筹备成立
the Marxist Theory Research Society.
马克思主义研究会
I can help you now.
现在身边能帮忙的
Chen Wangdao and Li Hanjun.
就是陈望道和李汉俊
Shiyan should also go abroad after a while.
过一段时间 世炎也该出国了
You guys are just in time.
你们来得正是时候啊
We come this time
我们俩这次来啊
just try and help you sir
本身就是想帮着先生
with the workers' movement together.
一起做工人运动的
So everything is at your disposal.
所以一切听您调遣
This workers' movement
这个工人运动呢
is a key point of our future work.
是我们今后工作的一个重点
This issue of our "New Youth"
我们这一期的《新青年》
is also a special issue to commemorate May Day International Labor Day.
也是纪念五一国际劳动节的专刊
But that's not the priority.
但是 当务之急还不是这个
The urgent matter
当务之急
is to build a national political party
是筹建一个全国性的政党
to lead the workers' movement.
来领导工人运动
When we were in Beijing,
我们在北京的时候
I heard Mr. Shouchang also talk about this matter.
听守常先生也说起过这个事情
Shouchang is in Peking University
守常在北京大学
establishing the Marxist Theory Research Society
成立了马克思学说研究会
and carrying out effective work.
并且开展了有效的工作
The political conditions in the south are better than those in the north.
这个南方的政治条件比北方好
We can't fall behind.
我们不能落后啊
Wangdao.
望道
Just in time.
正好
I'd like to introduce you to a new comrade.
我给你们介绍一位新同志
This is my assistant, Mr. Chen Wangdao.
这是我的助手陈望道先生
Mr. Chen.
陈先生
You two are here, too.
你们二位也在
You know each other.
你们认识
We do.
认识
We're colleagues in the "Weekly Review".
我们算是《星期评论》的同人
That's great.
那太好了
What do you want?
望道什么事
Sir, the "Communist Manifesto",
先生《共产党宣言》
I have translated it all.
我已经全部翻译好了
Please check, sir.
请先生校验
Great.
太好了
Wangdo, you have done a very important thing
望道 你为中国革命
for the Chinese revolution.
做了一件非常重要的事情
I believe history will never forget you.
我相信 历史不会忘记你
Great, sir.
太好了 先生
I'll stay up all night with you tonight.
今天晚上我就在您这儿熬个通宵
See for yourself.
先睹为快了
It's a pity.
遗憾得很
It can't printed it before you go abroad
你出国之前印不出来
and take it to France.
要不然 带到法国
It would be nice for Yannian and Qiaonian to see it.
这延年 乔年能看到该多好
It's fine.
没事
They can read the French version over there.
他们在那边可以看法文版的
Sir.
先生
One more thing.
还有一件事情
Say it.
说
It's okay. We're all comrades.
没关系 都是自己的同志
Just speak out what is in your mind.
但说无妨
Voitinsky, the international representative of the Communist Party
共产国际代表维经斯基
has arrived in Shanghai.
已经抵达上海
They brought Mr. Li Dazhao's
他们带来李大钊先生
letter of recommendation for you
给您的引荐信
and hope to see you soon.
希望能够尽快见到您
Can he speak Chinese?
他会说中国话吗
They brought an interpreter.
他们带来一个翻译
The Chinese name is Yang Mingzhai.
中国人 叫杨明斋
He's a member of the Russian Communist Party.
是俄共党员
This matter is very important.
这件事情很重要
They arranged to meet tomorrow.
明天 安排见面
This is Voitinsky.
这位是维经斯基
This is Chen Duxiu.
这位是陈独秀
Tell him to follow Chinese customs.
跟他讲 按中国的习俗来
Then let's shake hands.
那我们就握个手吧
This will do.
这个可以
Sit.
坐
I heard that Mr. Chen Duxiu
我听说陈独秀先生
is not particularly fond of Chinese traditional culture.
不是特别喜欢中国的传统文化
Nonsense. That's unfounded rumor.
瞎说 那是讹传
At the age of 8, I read four books and five classics with my grandfather.
我八岁随祖父熟读四书五经
At the age of 18, he won the first place in the academic examination.
十八岁中得院试秀才第一名
I speak confidently
自信地说
of Chinese cultural tradition.
中国的文化传统
It cannot be separated from my heart.
已经烂熟于心 挥之不去了
I want to ask Professor Chen.
想问一下陈教授
What do you think?
您是怎么看待
Marxism and the October Revolution in Russia.
马克思主义和俄国十月革命的
I think Marxism
我认为 马克思主义
is the most scientific theory in the world today.
是当今世界上最科学的理论
China's October Revolution road
我国的十月革命道路
is also an example for our Chinese revolution.
也是我们中国革命的榜样
That's great.
那太好了
Then we have a lot in common.
那我们有很多共同点了
Let me show you something.
有样东西给您看一下
Welcome, Comrade Voitinsky.
欢迎你 维经斯基同志
Sit.
坐
I am a member of the Far East Bureau of the Russian Communist Party.
我是俄共远东局的成员
This time, I was sent to China
这次受西伯利亚
by the Eastern Ethnic Branch of Siberia.
东方民族分部的派遣来到中国
Now I have arrived China
这次来中国
in the hope of contacting
希望能接触
comrades who believe in communism in China
中国信仰共产主义的同志
to discuss the possibility of establishing a party organization.
讨论建立党组织的可能性
I heard that Mr. Chen Duxiu
我听说陈独秀先生
is a famous Chinese thinker
是中国著名的思想家
and leader of mass movements.
和群众运动的领袖
Please give us your help.
请您给我们提供帮助
As early as February this year,
早在今年二月
I and Comrade Li Dazhao
我就和李大钊同志
have reached a consensus
已经就在中国建党的问题
on building a party in China.
达成了共识
After that, I made some substantive preparations.
之后呢 又实质性地做了一些准备工作
Like Peking University's.
比如北京大学的
Marxist Theory Research Society
马克思学说的研究会
and the future Shanghai's
和即将在上海成立的
Marxist Research Society,
马克思主义研究会
all these kinds of organizations.
都是这一类组织
Now, we are working hard to build a party.
我们现在呢正在抓紧建党
At the same time, I also hope to get
同时呢 也希望能够得到
Central Committee of the Communist Party of China and the Russian Communist Party
共产国际和俄共中央的
to mutually support and help each other.
支持和帮助
Great. Let's hug.
太好了 我们拥抱一下吧
I'm sorry, Comrade Voitinsky.
很抱歉 维经斯基同志
Embracing the Chinese tradition
拥抱在中国的传统中
means merging.
是合体的意思
Later,
之后呢
the Chinese and Russian parties
要成立的中国党和俄国党
can be allied but not combined.
可以结盟 但不可以合体
There is a tradition in China.
中国有个传统
Asking one's brothers to settle scores.
叫亲兄弟 明算账
You are you, I am me.
你是你 我是我
You can't lose yourself at any time.
什么时候都不能把自己弄没有了
So let's shake hands.
所以 我们还是握手吧
[April 1920, Voitinsky and other members of the Russian Communist Party approved by the Comintern arrived in China, met with Li Dazhao and Chen Duxiu, helped the Communist Party of China in its preparatory work.]
[1920年4月，经共产国际批准出的俄共产党员小组维经斯基等人到达中国，先后会贝了李大钊和陈独秀，对中国共产党的建党准备工作给子帮助。]
[Shanghai Workers' Club Evening School]
[上海工人俱乐部夜校]
Fellow workers.
各位工友
It's Labor Day soon.
这马上就五一劳动节了
This is our own festival.
这是我们自己的节日
We, the "New Youth" magazine,
我们《新青年》杂志社
is to publish a special commemorative issue for Labor Day,
要出版劳动节纪念号专刊
not only to publish articles
不仅要发表文章
but also to publish our workers'
还要发表我们工友们
own ideas and demands.
自己的主张和要求
Today
今天呢
is our evening class.
我们这堂夜校课
There are two main contents.
主要有两个内容
First,
第一
our editor of "New Youth",
是我们《新青年》编辑
Comrade Chen Wangdao,
陈望道同志
will give a speech.
来做一次演讲
Second,
第二
I hope you will be interested in this issue
希望大家对这一期的专
and put forward opinions and demands.
提出意见和要求
Hurrah!
好
Let's invite Comrade Chen Wangdao to give a speech now.
现在就请陈望道同志来做演讲
Comrades!
工人同志们
Who are the most useful people in the world?
世界上是些什么人最有用
Who are the most valuable?
最贵重呢
There will be a group of confused people who say
必有一班糊涂的人说
the Emperor is the most useful and valuable,
皇帝最有用 最贵重
or the scholar, or the bureaucrat
或是说做官的 读书的
is most useful and valuable.
最有用 最贵重
I thought they were wrong.
我以为他们说错了
I thought only the workers
我以为只有做工的人
are most useful and valuable.
最有用 最贵重
Hurrah!
好
The food we eat is made by the people working in the fields.
我们吃的粮食是那种田的人做的
Not by the Emperor, the President,
不是皇帝 总统
nor the bureaucrats.
做官的人做的
The clothes we wear are made by tailors.
我们穿的衣服是裁缝做的
Not by the Emperor, the President,
也不是皇帝 总统
nor the bureaucrats.
做官的人做的
The homes we live in
我们住的房屋
are made by carpenters and bricklayers.
是木匠 瓦匠 小工做的
Not by the Emperor, the President,
更不是皇帝 总统
nor the bureaucrats.
做官的人做的